Guide to the Ernst Bacon Papers, 1926-1990
Department of Special Collections
Bacon, Ernst. Papers,
1926-1990
M0943
Bacon, Ernst, 1898-
.75 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Primarily incoming correspondence, with only 4 retained carbons of Bacon's outgoing letters including one to Charles Ives. There is a high concentration of letters from the 1930s-1940s.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1996.
Biography
This collection represents a compilation of correspondence received by Ernst Bacon, and a few carbons of letters by him, between 1910 and 1989. During this time Bacon was an active participant in the musical community of the U.S., while maintaining friendships and collaborations with a variety of artists and musicians, both domestically and in Europe. Bacon and his wife were also active in the late 1920s and early 1930s in assisting artists and musicians to escape the growing Nazi movement. Bacon worked as a conductor and composer, as well as a professor of music. He directed the San Francisco Federal Music Project from 1935-1937. The majority of the correspondence, however, postdates this period and is generally of a more personal than professional nature. Some of the letters involve either soliciting recommendations or forwarding copies of recommendations for various honors among Bacon and his colleagues. Bacon's own accomplishment of achieving a Guggenheim Fellowship is recorded in a letter from the Guggenheim Foundation included in the collection.
Scope and Content
Most of Bacon's correspondents were involved in the music community in some fashion, from composers, to musicians, to critics. Notable correspondents include Ernest Bloch, Eugene Goosens, Otto and Ethel Luening, and George Szell. However, Bacon fostered friendships with other artists as well, including author Henry Cowell and his wife, Sidney. The letters in this collection date from Cowell's incarceration in San Quentin. There are also letters from Tillie Olsen and Upton Sinclair. Since the collection is made up entirely of correspondence, it has not been divided into Series. Whenever possible, items have been processed by individual names, resulting in 93 folders arranged alphabetically by individual, and 2 remaining folders arranged by date.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Ameling, Amy.; Barnes, Matt.; Bauer, Harold, 1873-1951.; Bloch, Ernest, 1885-1977.; Boyle, Kay, 1902-; Bufano, Beniamino, 1898-1970.; Bynner, Witter, 1881-1968.; Corcoran, Thomas.; Cowell, Henry, 1897-1965.; Cowell, Sidney Robertson.; Curtain, Phyllis.; Dixon, Maynard, 1875-1946.; Donat, Peter, 1928-; Downes, Edward, 1911-; Eloesser, Leo.; Erskine, John, 1879-1951.; Faurâe, Gabriel, 1845-1924.; Field, Sara Bard, 1882-1974.; Foldes, Andor, 1913-; Gautier, Eva.; Glenn, Carroll.; Goosens, Boonie.; Goosens, Eugene, Sir, 1893-1962.; Goldman, Maurice.; Gould, Morton, 1913-; Hanson, Howard, 1896-; Huntington, Hartford, 1911-; Horgan, Paul, 1903-; Houston, George F.; Hurd, Henrietta.; Hurd, Peter.; Ives, Charles, 1874-1954.; Jalowetz, Heinrich.; Kindler, Hans, 1892-1949.; Krasner, Louis, 1903-; Kurenko, Maria.; Lehmann, Lotte, 1888-1976.; Lee, Russel.; Lockwood, Normand, 1906-; Loesser, Arthur, 1894-1969.; Lomax, Alan, 1915-; Lorenz, Adolf, 1854-1946.; Lubin, Ernest.; Luening, Otto, 1900-; Luening, Ethel.; MacDowell, Edward, Mrs.; Martino, Donald, 1931-; Harrison, Guy Fraser, 1894-1986.; Harrison, Lou, 1917-; Moe, Henry Allen, 1894-1975.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-; Newhall, Nancy Wynne.; Nies-Berger, Edouard.; Nordoff, Paul, 1909-; Nowak, Lionel, 1911-; Olsen, Tillie.; Piazzini, Gottardo.; Pinza, Ezio.; Pleasants, Henry.; Ross, Hugh, 1898-; Rowell, Margaret Avery, 1900-; Saben, Mowry.; Saminsky, Lazare, 1882-1959.; Schumann, Elisabeth.; Sebastian, John, 1944-; Sharp, Cecil, 1859-1924.; Shaw, Robert, 1916-; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968.; Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1894-; Sokoloff, Vladimir.; Sowerby, Leo, 1895-1968.; Stackpole, Ralph, 1885-1973.; Stock, Frederick, 1872-1942.; Szell, George, 1897-1970.; Szigeti, Joseph, 1892-1973.; Thompson, Randall, 1899-; Thomson, Virgil, 1896-; Tinayre, Yves, 1891-1972.; Toch, Ernst, 1887-1964.; Warfield, William.; Weigl, Karl, 1881-1949.; Whedon, Harriet.; Wood, Charles Erskine Scott, 1852-1944.; American literature--20th century.; Art, Modern--20th century--California.; Music--20th century--California.
Collection Contents
- Ameling, Elly - soprano (1979) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bacon, Ernst - photos and carbons of letters (1939) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Barnes, Matt - artist (1944) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bauer, Harold - pianist (1931-44) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Baumberger, Carl (1945-46) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bloch, Ernest - composer (1956) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Boyle, Kay - American expatriate author (1962) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bufano, Ben - artist (1933) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Chasins, Abram (1962, 1981) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Corocan, Thomas - student of Paul Horgan (1972-73) (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Cowell, Henry - composer (1938-39, 1953) (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Cowell, Sidney [Mrs. Henry] (1952, 1983) (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Curtin, Phyllis - (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Dixon, Maynard - artist (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Donat, Peter - actor (1977) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Downes, Edwin - music critic (1940-46) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Eloesser, Leo - thoracic surgeon (1932-74, including some n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Erskine, John - author & critic (1941, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Fairbank, Janet - soprano (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Fauré, Gabriel - French composer - cover (1910) (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Field, Sara Bard - poet (1931-49, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Foldes, Andor - pianist (1946-63) (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Gautier, Eva - singer (1948, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Glenn, Carroll - violinist (1945, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Goldman, Maurice (1947, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Goldman, Richard Franko - bandmaster & composer (1966) (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Goossens, Boonie [Mrs. Eugene] - including photo (1926, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Goossens, Eugene - composer & conductor (1928-47) (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Gould, Morton - president of ASCAP (1987, 1989) (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Hanson, Howard - composer (1975) (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Harris, Roy - director of Int'l Institute of Music (1961) (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Harrison, Guy - musical director (1946, 1955) (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Harrison, Lou - composer (1987) (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Hartford, Huntington - critic (1964) (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Horgan, Paul - friend & colleague (1978, 1982) (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Houston, George - singer (1927, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Hurd, Henrietta [Mrs. Peter, sister of Andrew Wyeth] (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Hurd, Peter - artist (1980) (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Jalowetz, Heinrich - music professor (1942) (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Kindler, Hans - conductor (1941) (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Krasner, Louis - violinist (1926) (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Kurenko, Maria - singer (1946, 1953) (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Lang, Paul Henry (1950, 1981, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Lehman, Lotte - singer (1968) (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Lee, Russel - founder Palo Alto Clinic (1956, 1973-74, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Lockwood, Normand - composer (1948-81) (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Loesser, Arthur - conductor (1941) (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Lomax, Alan - musicologist (1945) (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Lorenz, Adolf - inventor (1921) (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Lubin, Ernest - music book editor (1968-72) (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Luening, Otto [composer & conductor] & Ethel [musician] (1930-91) (Box 1, Folder 51)
- MacDowell, Mrs. Edward - wife of composer (1936-55, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Martino, Don - composer (1952, 1972) (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Moe, Henry Allen - secretary, Guggenheim Foundation (1939, 1941) (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Mumford, Lewis - author (1963) (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Newhall, Nancy [Mrs. Beaumont] (1952-66) (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Nies-Berger, Eduoard - concert pianist (1948) (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Nordoff, Paul - composer & author (1971-72, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Nowak, Lionel - composer & pianist (1932-90) (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Olsen, Tillie - author (n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Pattison, Lee (1937-58) (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Piazinni, Gottardo - painter (1939, photo 1938) (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Pinza, Ezio - opera singer (1945) (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Pleasants, Henry - composer (1963) (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Reis, Claire - chairwoman, League of Composers (1941, 1975, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Rethberg, Elizabeth (photo, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Ross, Hugh - organist & conductor (1938-1950) (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Rowell, Margaret [Mrs. Galen] (1985, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Saben, Mowry - writer (1935-40) (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Saminsky, Lazare - composer, conductor, & writer (1951) (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Schuman, Elizabeth - singer (1939) (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Sebastian, John - pianist (1948, n.d.) (Box 1, Folder 72)
- Sharp, Cecil - muiscologist (1954) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Shaw, Robert - chorale director (1954-57, n.d.) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Sinclair, Upton - author (1941) (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Slominsky, Nicholas - editor (1950, 1970, 1974) (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Sokoloff, Vladimir - director, Curtis Institute of Music (1962-87) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Sowerby, Leo - organist & composer (1933-66) (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Stackpole, Ralph - artist (1952) (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Stock, Frederich - violinist, conductor, & composer (1939-40) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Szell, George - conductor (1944, 1955) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Szigeti, Joseph - violinist (1944-46) (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Thomas, John Charles - baritone (1939) (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Thompson, Randall - composer (1939) (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Thomson, Virgil - composer (1953) (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Tinayre, Yves - tenor, research scholar (1948-57) (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Toch, Ernst - composer & pianist (1954) (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Ussher, Bruno David - colleague through the San Francisco Federal Music Project (1939, n.d.) (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Warfield, William - bass singer (1950) (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Weigl, Karl - composer (1938-45, n.d.) (Box 2, Folder 18)
- West, Marie - poet (picture and poem from The Otherwise, published 1976) (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Whedon, Harriet - artist (1938-51, n.d.) (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Wood, Charles Erskine Scott - poet (picture 1928, poem "O! Alabama" n.d.) (Box 2, Folder 21)
- General Correspondence (1932-60) (Box 2, Folder 22)
- General Correspondence (1961-89, n.d.) (Box 2, Folder 23)